Guide to the United Brotherhood Of Carpenters And Joiners Of America, Local #88 (Anaconda) Records 1889-1967
Montana Historical Society Archives
United Brotherhood Of Carpenters And Joiners Of America, Local #88 (Anaconda) Records
1889-1967
Montana Historical Society, Research Center Archives 225 N. Roberts PO Box 201201 Helena MT 59620-1201 (406) 444-4774 mhslibrary@mt.gov
MC 194
United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 88 (Anaconda, Mont.)
13 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local #88 in Anaconda, Montana, consist of general correspondence (1890s-1950s); minute books (1889-1965); daybooks (1896-1964); membership dues books (1896-1965). Also included are records of Deer Lodge Local #1229; the Montana State Council of Carpenters; the national union; the Montana State Federation of Labor/Montana State AFL-CIO; the Montana Apprenticeship Council; and the Non-Ferrous Metals Council.
The United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America was founded in 1881 by Peter J. McGuire and Gustav Luebkert. In April of that year the two men formed a provisional committee and started the newspaper The Carpenter to promote the idea of a national union of carpenters. The first convention of the Brotherhood was held in Chicago in August of 1881. Like many unions of the period the Brotherhood grew out of a tradition of social democracy and socialism. The early preamble reflected this in its call for a "Cooperative Commonwealth" with trade unions as its cornerstone. The union's immediate goals included wage and hour demands and death and sickness benefits. The union grew rapidly; its 1881 membership of 2000 expanded to 50,000 by 1890, and 100,000 by 1900. In May 1889 an organizational meeting was held in Anaconda, Montana, to form a local carpenters' union. The first formal meeting of the new Local #88, of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America was held on June 6, 1889 by nine charter members. Anthony Blise was elected president and George Owen, recording secretary. The reform ideology of the national union was reflected in the local bylaws, the preamble to which stated that "We hold it as a sacred duty to posterity to use our utmost endeavor to replace the present wage system by cooperative industry and to claim our inalienable right to the means of living which are inherent in the soil." The Anaconda local bylaws fined members for patronizing Chinese businessmen. Both the preamble and the anti-Chinese clause were eliminated in later bylaws. The union's main concerns were promoting the eight hour day, protecting wages, providing sick and death insurance, enforcing union shop conditions, and protecting the jurisdiction of the union against other unions. In 1915 the carpenters formed a statewide organization, the Montana State Council of Carpenters, to coordinate the work of all the locals in Montana. The carpenters' union was also active in the Montana State Federation of Labor, the Montana State AFL-CIO, the Montana State Apprenticeship Council, and the Non-ferrous Metals Council. The latter was a joint negotiating team of unions in the regional copper industry.
Content Description:
This collection consists of records of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local #88 (Anaconda). In addition there are smaller subgroups of records for Deer Lodge Local #1229, the Montana State Council of Carpenters, the national union, the Montana State Federation of Labor/Montana State AFL-CIO, the Montana State Apprenticeship Council, and the Non-ferrous Metals Council. The Anaconda Local #88 records include incoming and outgoing correspondence (1895-1966); financial records (1896-1965), including daybooks, hall rental ledgers, and membership dues records; minutes (1889-1965); organizational records (1894-1958), including bylaws and membership applications; reports (1895-1967), including sick committee reports and a report of the local walking delegate regarding union and non-union jobs around Anaconda; subject files (1938-1957), including a jurisdictional dispute with the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees over carpenters employed by the Butte, Anaconda, and Pacific Railway; and miscellany. Records of the smaller subgroups include Deer Lodge Local #1229 financial records (1956-1965), minutes (1961-1966), and organizational records (1965); national union financial records (1905-1928), legal documents (1931-1953), minutes (1904, 1936, 1955-1957), and organizational records (1903, 1929-1941); \b Montana State Council of Carpenters correspondence (1956-1957), financial recoeds (1939-1967), legal documents (1956), and minutes (1949-1957); \b Montana Apprenticeship Council\b0 correspondence (1941-1947), minutes (1942-1946), annual reports (1942, 1946), and miscellany; \b Montana State Federation of Labor/ AFL-CIO\b0 financial records (1956-1961) and minutes (1957); and \b Non-ferrous Metals Council\b0 minutes (1952), organizational materials (1951-1952), and legal documents (1951-1952). [Printed material has been transferred to the Library. Montana State Federation of Labor/ AFL-CIO materials were transferred to the Montana State AFL-CIO Records.]
Arrangement:
by series
Acquisition Information:
available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Apprentices; Chinese; Genealogy; Labor unions--Carpenters; World War, 1939-1945--War work; Deer Lodge (Mont.); Anaconda (Mont.); Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 88 (Anaconda, Mont.)
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (includes appeals from national unions; U.S. Industrial Commission), 1895-1904 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
    - Miscellaneous (includes founding manifesto of Industrial Workers of the World [IWW] and American Federation of Labor [AFL]; proposed incorporation of Anaconda union hall), 1905-1906 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
    - Miscellaneous (includes resignation of local officers; proposed split in local union), 1907 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
    - Miscellaneous (includes appeals from other unions; charges against member for violating bylaws), 1908 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
    - Miscellaneous (includes World War I; relations with other unions), 1914-1931 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
    - Miscellaneous (includes jurisdictional issues; teachers union at University of Montana; hours of work at Anaconda Copper Mining Company), 1935-1939 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
    - Miscellaneous (includes World War II production; anti-labor legislation; forest fire; Building and Metal Trade Council; lumber workers' strike in Columbia Falls; Unemployment Compensation Commission of Montana ruling re unemployment benefits for strikers), 1940-1942 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
    - Miscellaneous (includes World War II and post-war labor changes; relations with Anaconda Copper Mining Company and Montana State Hospital; dispute between Texas local and national union), 1943-1948 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
    - Miscellaneous (includes relations with Anaconda Copper Mining Company; non-union carpentry work; changes in local bylaws, relations with Montana State Hospital; State Council of Carpenters; jurisdictional issues; apprenticeship), 1949-1950 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
    - Miscellaneous (includes Montana State Federation of labor circular letters; UBCJA withdrawal from AFL; former member's complaint against local), 1951-1953 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
    - Miscellaneous (includes work on Anaconda schools; state game farm at Warm Springs; "right-to-work" laws), 1954-1966 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
    - Sympathy thank-you notes, n.d. (Box-folder 1 / 12)
    - Telegrams (re jurisdictional matters), 1892, 1946-1950 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous (includes union activities by University of Montana professors; cost of living; Japanese workers; relations with Anaconda Copper Mining Company and Montana State Hospital; non-union carpentry work in Anaconda), 1939-1950 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
    - Miscellaneous (includes dispute with Andrew Tuss re non-union labor; internal matters; relations with other unions, etc.), 1951-1965 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Anaconda Building and Metal Trades Council to National Labor Relations Board (re negotiations with Anaconda Copper Mining Company), 1963 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Financial Records
    - Auditor's monthly reports, 1897-1927 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
    - Bills, receipts, etc. [sampled], 1895-1944 (Box-folder 2 / 2)
    - Cash book, 1941-1950 (Box-folder 2 / 3)
    - Day books, 1896-1904, 1910-1922 (Box-folder 2 / 4-8)
    - Day books, 1922-1942 (Box-folder 3 / 1-8)
    - Day books, 1942-1952 (Box-folder 4 / 1-11)
    - Day books, 1952-1961 (Box-folder 5 / 1-11)
    - Day books, 1961-1964 (Box-folder 6 / 1-3)
    - Financial Secretary's monthly reports, 1897, 1920-1925 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
    - Hall rental ledger (also includes raffle ticket receipts, 1912-1918), 1903-1906 (Box-folder 6 / 5)
    - Hall rental ledger (also includes list of members in good standing, n.d.), 1906-1929 (Box-folder 6 / 6)
    - Hall rental ledger (also includes lists of officers, 1937-1943), 1930-1938 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
    - Journal, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
    - Members' dues record (includes age, initiation date, residence), 1896-1909 (Box-folder 7 / 1-4)
    - Members' dues record, 1910-1916 (Box-folder 8 / 1-4)
    - Members' dues record, 1917-1925 (Box-folder 9 / 1-4)
    - Members' dues record, 1926-1938 (Box-folder 10 / 1-4)
    - Members' dues record, 1939-1946 (Box-folder 11 / 1-4)
    - Members' dues record (includes age, initiation date, residence), 1946-1948 (Box-folder 12 / 1)
    - Members' dues record: A-H, 1950-1965 (Box-folder 12 / 2-6)
    - Members' dues record: I-Sm, 1950-1965 (Box-folder 13 / 1-6)
    - Members' dues record: So-Z, 1950-1965 (Box-folder 14 / 1-3)
    - Monthly report to Carpenters' State Council of Montana, 1920-1923, 1938=1940 (Box-folder 14 / 4-5)
    - Officers' bond applications and bond reports, 1939, 1960 (Box-folder 14 / 6)
    - Per capita tax to national union, 1892 (Box-folder 14 / 7)
    - Quarterly account sheets (lists members, clearance cards granted, members in arrears, etc.), 1950, 1955-1959 (Box-folder 15 / 1-5)
    - Reports to National Labor Relations board [NLRB], 1957 (Box-folder 16 / 1)
    - Reports to Unemployment Compensation Commission of Montana, 1941-1960 (Box-folder 16 / 2)
    - Reports to U.S. Dept. of Labor, 1957-1959 (Box-folder 16 / 3)
    - Treasurer's cash book, 1905-1906 (Box-folder 16 / 4)
    - Treasurer's remittance blank, 1920-1926 (Box-folder 16 / 5)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1897-1898 (Box-folder 16 / 6)
    - Trustees' financial reports, 1897-1898, 1904-1908 (Box-folder 16 / 7)
    - U.S. Internal Revenue Service employee's tax return, 1936-1960 (Box-folder 16 / 8)
    - U.S. Internal Revenue Service return of tax-exempt organization, 1949, 1954 (Box-folder 16 / 9)
  - Hearings
    - Hearing beford Nonferrous Metals Commission of the National War Labor in the matter of the Anaconda Copper Mining Company and the Building and Construction Trades Dept., AFL and the Metal Trades Council, AFL, 1942 (Box-folder 16 / 10)
  - Legal Documents
    - Agreements between Anaconda Copper Mining Company and the Building and Construction Trades Council, et al., 1936-1956 (Box-folder 16 / 11)
    - Agreements with Montana Power Company, 1937 (Box-folder 16 / 12)
    - Agreements with building contractors, 1948-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 16 / 13)
    - Lodge hall license, 1935 (Box-folder 16 / 14)
  - Minutes
    - Executive committee minutes, Feb.-June 1933 (Box-folder 16 / 15)
    - Minute books, May 1889- Aug. 1895 (Box-folder 16 / 16-17)
    - Minute books, Sept. 1895- June 1906 (Box-folder 17 / 1-4)
    - Minute books (1908-1909 includes sick committee reports, 1924-1929), July 1906- July 1916 (Box-folder 18 / 1-4)
    - Minute books, July 1916- Sept. 1932, Nov. 1935- May 1941 (Box-folder 19 / 1-5)
    - Minute books, May 1941- July 1954, Sept.1958- June 1965 (Box-folder 20 / 1-4)
    - Committee reports, etc. [removed from minute books], 1895 (Box-folder 20 / 5)
    - Resolutions [removed from minute books], 1897-1962 (Box-folder 20 / 6)
    - Resolutions of respect for deceased members [removed from minute books], 1892, 1907-1944 (Box-folder 20 / 7)
  - Organization
    - Bylaws, 1929, 1947, n.d. (Box-folder 21 / 1)
    - Membership applications: A-Y, 1894-1896, 1900 (Box-folder 21 / 2-5)
    - Membership applications, 1914-1916, 1928-1948 (Box-folder 21 / 6-10)
    - Suspended and transferred members' membership applications, 1958 (Box-folder 21 / 11)
    - Vote of Local #88 on national union constitutional amendements, 1896, 1950, 1954 (Box-folder 21 / 12)
  - Printed Material
    - List of printed material transferred to Library (Box-folder 21 / 13)
  - Reports
    - Report of walking delegate (re union and non-union carpentry work being done), 1895 (Box-folder 21 / 14)
    - Sick committee reports (see minute book 1908-1909 for reports 1924-1929), 1918-1923 (Box-folder 21 / 15)
    - Sick committee reports, 1929-1967 (Box-folder 22 / 1-2)
  - Subject Files
    - Charles Johnson case (re arbitration in dispute between Park Motors of Anaconda and several unions), 1938 (Box-folder 22 / 3)
    - Jurisdictional dispute with Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees to represent carpenters employed by Butte, Anaconda and Pacific Railway Company, 1938-1955, 1957 (Box-folder 22 / 4-5)
  - Miscellany
    - Affidavit of Ben Goodman (re employment of Anaconda Copper Mining Company carpenters after hours), 1953 (Box-folder 22 / 6)
    - American Federation of Labor bulletins (re Taft-Hartley Act), 1947 (Box-folder 22 / 7)
    - American Federation of Labor constitution and outline, 1903 (Box-folder 22 / 8)
    - Anaconda Copper Mining Company carpenter shop seniority lists, 1942-1951 (Box-folder 22 / 9)
    - Charity appeals, 1940s (Box-folder 22 / 10)
    - Directory of labor organizations in Montana, 1947 (Box-folder 22 / 11)
    - List of carpentry shops using union label, 1952 (Box-folder 22 / 12)
    - Petition to Montana legislature for initiative and referendum, ca. 1905 (Box-folder 22 / 13)
    - Report on Institute on the New Labor Law (re Landrum-Griffin Bill), 1959 (Box-folder 22 / 14)
    - "Statement of grievance of Robert Kedey concerning the action of certain members of Local Union #88 of Anaconda, Montana", 1906 (Box-folder 22 / 15)
    - Trade rules of Local #88, 1947, 1953 (Box-folder 22 / 16)
    - "Unfair list" (re non-union shops), 1905 (Box-folder 22 / 17)
    - World War II programs and politics, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 22 / 18)
    - Miscellaneous (blank forms, union cards, credentials, song sheet, invitations, etc.), 1905-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 22 / 19)
- United Brotherhood Of Carpenters And Joiners Of America, Local #1229 (Deer Lodge)
  - Financial Records
    - Bond reports, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 23 / 1)
    - Check and deposit registers, 1956-1966 (Box-folder 23 / 2-4)
    - Savings book, 1955-1966 (Box-folder 23 / 5)
    - U.S. Internal Revenue Service return of tax exempt organization, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 23 / 6)
  - Minutes
    - Minute book, 1961-1966 (Box-folder 23 / 7)
  - Organization
    - Lists of officers and members' roll call, Aug.-Sept. 1965 (Box-folder 23 / 8)
- United Brotherhood Of Carpenters And Joiners Of America, (National Union)
  - Financial Records
    - Financial statements of general secretary, 1905-1908, 1928 (Box-folder 23 / 9)
    - Union supplies price lists, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 23 / 10)
  - Legal Documents
    - Jurisdictional agreements with other building trades unions, 1931-1953, n.d. (Box-folder 23 / 11)
  - Minutes
    - General convention proceedings, 1904, 1936 (Box-folder 23 / 12)
    - General Executive Board minutes, 1955, 1957 (Box-folder 23 / 13)
    - Sixth District Conference minutes, Seattle, Wash., 1953 (Box-folder 23 / 14)
  - Organization
    - Constitution and bylaws, 1929-1941 (Box-folder 23 / 15)
    - "Plan of amalgamation of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America and the Amalgamated Society of Carpenters and Joiners", 1903 (Box-folder 23 / 16)
  - Miscellany
    - "Current Information" newsletter, 1948-1955, 1960 (Box-folder 23 / 17)
    - Statement of General Executive Board (re withdrawal from AFL over jurisdictional problems), 1953 (Box-folder 23 / 18)
- Montana State Council Of Carpenters
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1956 (Box-folder 23 / 19)
  - Financial Records
    - Audit reports (lists of employers and their carpenters union employees), 1966-1967 (Box-folder 24 / 1-4)
    - Eligibility reports (lists of union members in good standing statewide), 1966-1967 (Box-folder 24 / 5-7)
    - Employer reporting status, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 24 / 8)
    - Financial reports, 1939-1957 (Box-folder 25 / 1)
  - Legal Documents
    - Contract with Montana Contractors' Association, 1956 (Box-folder 25 / 2)
  - Minutes
    - Convention minutes, 1949, 1956-1958, 1961 (Box-folder 25 / 3-7)
    - Executive committee minutes, 1957 (Box-folder 25 / 8)
  - Organization
    - Convention program, 1938 (Box-folder 25 / 9)
    - Proposed changes in constitution and bylaws, 1956 (Box-folder 25 / 10)
  - Reports
    - Reports to local unions, 1956 (Box-folder 25 / 11)
- Montana State Apprenticeship Council
  - General Correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, 1941-1947 (Box-folder 25 / 12)
  - Financial Records
    - Suggested budgets, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 25 / 13)
  - Minutes
    - Minutes and agendas, 1942-1946 (Box-folder 25 / 14)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports, 1942, 1946 (Box-folder 25 / 15)
    - "Report...on the appointment of the Montana State Apprenticeship Council as the qualifying agency for establishments to train on-the-job veterans in trades below apprenticeship levels", 1945 (Box-folder 25 / 16)
  - Miscellany
    - Certificate of appreciation [OVERSIZE], n.d. (Box-folder 25 / 17)
    - Legislative bills re apprenticeship, n.d. (Box-folder 25 / 18)
    - "Lists of approved industrial establishments to train veterans in the apprenticeship trades...under G.I. Bill", 1945-1947 (Box-folder 25 / 19)
    - Standards of apprenticeship, 1941, 1956 (Box-folder 25 / 20)
    - U.S. Dept. of Labor Apprenticeship Training Service materials, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 25 / 21)
    - Washington State Apprenticeship Council materials, 1942 (Box-folder 25 / 22)
    - Western states carpenter, cabinet, and millmen apprenticeship contest, 1959 (Box-folder 25 / 23)
    - Qualifications for members: list of apprenticeable trades; approval of industrial institutions; etc., 1947, n.d. (Box-folder 25 / 24)
- Non-ferrous Metals Council
  - Minutes
    - Minutes, 1952 (Box-folder 25 / 25)
  - Organization
    - Constitution; bylaws, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 25 / 26)
  - Miscellany
    - Exerpts from contracts with copper companies (re job classification and wage scales), 1951-1952 (Box-folder 25 / 27)